<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gains Are Modest For Nasdaq Index</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="WALL STREET IN 1986"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OVER-THE-COUNTER TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED91E3EF931A35752C0A961948260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gains Are Modest For Nasdaq Index</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After a bull market of more than four years, it might be expected that the over-the-counter stocks would be frothing, but their moderate gains in 1986 failed to keep pace with those in other markets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After a bull market of more than four years, it might be expected that the over-the-counter stocks would be frothing, but their moderate gains in 1986 failed to keep pace with those in other markets.</p>
        <p>After a bull market of more than four years, it might be expected that the over-the-counter stocks would be frothing, but their moderate gains in 1986 failed to keep pace with those in other markets.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index of over-the-counter stocks closed Wednesday at 348.83, up from 324.93 at the beginning of 1986. The 7.4 percent gain was far outdistanced by the 22.6 percent rise for the year posted by the Dow Jones industrial average, an indicator based on 30 blue-chip stocks traded on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>The gain measured by the over-the-counter index also failed to approach the 13.98 percent increase in the broad-based New York Stock Exchange composite index during 1986. More Issues Traded</p>
        <p>At year-end, the aggregate market value of the Nasdaq common stocks stood at a record $343 billion, up from $285 billion at the end of 1985 -thanks in part to the addition of nearly 400 stocks, bringing the total of issues traded to 5,071.</p>
        <p>Gordon S. Macklin, president of the National Association of Securities Dealers, said that the Nasdaq index's gains came from strong performances in such sectors as pharmaceuticals, utilities and finance, and from the services sector, which benefited from lower interest rates and low inflation.</p>
        <p>Analysts depicted the general over-the-counter market as being in a lull. ''Over-the-counter stocks haven't done anything to speak of since last summer,'' said William M. LeFevre, senior vice president at Advest Group Inc. ''I don't see this market topping out without a rally in the Nasdaq.''</p>
        <p>Among all Nasdaq stock groups, the biggest gainer was the 102-company pharmaceutical and biotechnology group, which was up 55 percent. It was followed closely by apparel companies, which rose 51 percent. Gold and silver issues gained 31 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>Rounding out the top five groups were electric, gas and sanitary services - which were up 23 percent -and trucking and transportation companies, with an 18 percent rise. Banks Fare Poorly</p>
        <p>Commercial banks, particularly in the Southwest, posted the biggest decline with a 28 percent drop. They were followed by electronic components, which fell 24 percent. Oil and gas companies dropped 23 percent, and communications equipment companies and construction concerns declined 17 percent and 11 percent, respectively.</p>
        <p>Among the top gaining Nasdaq issues, there seemed to be little in common. They included a mining company, a slot machine maker and a producer of lawn-care equipment.</p>
        <p>The top gainer was Digitech Inc., an electronic equipment manufacturer in St. Louis. The company has been reporting improved earnings and had a gain on the sale of discontinued operations. For the year, its stock jumped 776 percent, to $5.75.</p>
        <p>The biggest loser was the Spectran Corporation of Sturbridge, Mass., which makes flexible glass fibers for the communications industry. The company posted a loss because of a $2.1 million inventory write-down. Spectran's stock fell 90.1 percent for the year, to $2.125.</p>
        <p>The list of the top 10 losers included financial institutions that suffered from huge loan losses. Among them were banks in Alaska and Oklahoma, where declining crude oil prices have severely damaged local economies.  MOST ACTIVE NASDAQ ISSUES IN 1986</p>
        <p>Volume</p>
        <p>Change</p>
        <p>(Millions of</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>from</p>
        <p>Stocks</p>
        <p>Shares)</p>
        <p>High</p>
        <p>Low</p>
        <p>Close</p>
        <p>1985</p>
        <p>MCI</p>
        <p>447.1</p>
        <p>13 1/4</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>6 1/4</p>
        <p>-5</p>
        <p>Glaxo Holding</p>
        <p>276.7</p>
        <p>17 3/4</p>
        <p>10 7/8</p>
        <p>15 3/8</p>
        <p>+4 3/8</p>
        <p>Jaguar</p>
        <p>254.1</p>
        <p>9 1/4</p>
        <p>4 5/8</p>
        <p>7 15/16</p>
        <p>+3</p>
        <p>Apple Computer</p>
        <p>238.0</p>
        <p>43 7/8</p>
        <p>21 3/4</p>
        <p>40 1/2</p>
        <p>+18 1/2</p>
        <p>Intel</p>
        <p>192.5</p>
        <p>32 1/4</p>
        <p>16 3/8</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>-8 1/4</p>
        <p>Seagate</p>
        <p>176.7</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>7 1/8</p>
        <p>19 1/8</p>
        <p>+11 7/8</p>
        <p>Henley Group</p>
        <p>130.0</p>
        <p>24 1/4</p>
        <p>17 1/4</p>
        <p>22 5/8</p>
        <p>-</p>
        <p>Convergent Tech.</p>
        <p>121.9</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>4 1/8</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>-5 7/8</p>
        <p>Intergraph Corp.</p>
        <p>121.4</p>
        <p>40 1/2</p>
        <p>15 1/4</p>
        <p>17</p>
        <p>-19 3/4</p>
        <p>THT Lyd</p>
        <p>117.3</p>
        <p>8 3/4</p>
        <p>1 1/4</p>
        <p>2 13/16</p>
        <p>+1 9/16</p>
        <p>U.S. Health Care</p>
        <p>113.6</p>
        <p>22 7/8</p>
        <p>11 1/8</p>
        <p>11 5/8</p>
        <p>-8 3/4</p>
        <p>Tandon Corp.</p>
        <p>113.2</p>
        <p>7 7/8</p>
        <p>1 7/8</p>
        <p>2 5/16</p>
        <p>-2 9/16</p>
        <p>HBO</p>
        <p>112.4</p>
        <p>18 1/4</p>
        <p>8 1/2</p>
        <p>9 1/4</p>
        <p>-9 1/8</p>
        <p>DSC Communications</p>
        <p>106.1</p>
        <p>12 3/4</p>
        <p>5 3/8</p>
        <p>5 3/4</p>
        <p>-3 1/4</p>
        <p>Tandem Computers</p>
        <p>104.1</p>
        <p>39 1/2</p>
        <p>19 1/2</p>
        <p>34 1/4</p>
        <p>+12</p>
        <p>WALL STREET IN 1986</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
