<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dr. Reinhold Benesch, Biochemist, Dies at 67</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Obituary" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="97"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENESCH, REINHOLD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD1E3CF932A35752C0A961948260" item-length="213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dr. Reinhold Benesch, Biochemist, Dies at 67</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Reinhold Benesch, a biochemist best known for his study of red blood cells, died of complications arising from lymphatic cancer, at Columbia-Presyterian Medical Center Tuesday. He was 67 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Reinhold Benesch, a biochemist best known for his study of red blood cells, died of complications arising from lymphatic cancer, at Columbia-Presyterian Medical Center Tuesday. He was 67 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Dr. Reinhold Benesch, a biochemist best known for his study of red blood cells, died of complications arising from lymphatic cancer, at Columbia-Presyterian Medical Center Tuesday. He was 67 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Dr. Benesch and his wife, Dr. Ruth Erica Benesch, were professors of biochemistry and shared a research laboratory at the College of Physicians and Surgeons at Columbia University. Their collaboration focused on the mechanisms by which hemoglobin transports oxygen to living tissues.</p>
        <p>In 1966 he and his wife discovered that an organic phosphorous compound, 2,3-diphosphoglycerate, plays a key role in loosening the bonds between hemoglobin and oxygen, thereby improving the flow of oxygen from blood to the tissues.</p>
        <p>Dr. Benesch was born in Poland on Aug. 13, 1919, and immigrated to England, where he received a bachelor's degree from Leeds University in 1941. Later, he became a naturalized citizen of the United States and received a doctorate in biochemistry at Northwestern University. Dr. Benesch was affiliated with Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and since 1966 held the concurrent position of professor of biochemistry at Columbia.</p>
        <p>In addition to his wife, he is survived by a daughter, Susan, and a son, Andrew, both of New York City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
